hi I'm broken turist this video I'm
going to address something really really
important for strength coaches personal
trainers physical therapists just you
know this is a very important topic and
it's on it's on lumbar pelvic hip
functioning and this is this carries
over to low back pain you know posture
performance power speed strength so it's
incredibly important and I've been
having a lot of success both with people
that I work with as well as feedback
I've received from around the world from
people who have been implementing some
of my methods and in this video I want
to explain my rationale as to why this
is going on so here I've got a model and
it's a skeletal model of the spine the
pelvis and the hips so first let me go
over ranges of motion here this here is
the hip the hip joint and this would be
hip flexion and this is hip extension so
you know you move the hips through hip
flexion and hip extension when you squat
when you lunge when you sprint when you
jump all right now
this is the lumbar spine these lower
five vertebrae in the spine and the
lumbar spine and the pelvis and the hip
all work together this is why they're
called the lumbo-pelvic hip complex
because they all work together in a
coordinated fashion and you need to have
proper lumbo-pelvic hip complex
functioning for all sorts of reasons for
proper spinal health for proper load
transfer for ideal performance and and
even for ideal posture so let me just
let me now we know the hip my hip
flexion extension the pelvis also moves
so the pelvis can tilt forward and
backwards so if it tilts this way this
is anterior pelvic tilt and if it tilts
this way this is posterior pelvic
so aunt your tilt posture tilt and the
lumbar spine here when it rounds over
this is flexion and then this is
extension and then when it goes past
anatomical position this is
hyperextension so if you notice with a
lumbar spine when these get further
apart when they spread apart what you
notice here is that you're going to be
putting more pressure see the front and
rear portion of the vertebrae they're
going to be pinching together and this
is why you can see a little herniated
disk here these portions pinch together
you know so you've got an approximation
on the anterior side and a distraction
on the posterior side and that is going
to call the nucleus to exhibit more
pressure rearward and you get the most
herniation in a postural lateral fashion
right there and that's what happens with
too much lumbar flexion is you can get
Ernie ations there all right on the flip
side when you have lumbar hyperextension
as you can see here you can get these
posterior elements of the spine then jam
together and this is dangerous for the
whole posterior portions of these the
the lumbar vertebrae and this is
dangerous as well this can lead to
chronic injury chronic injury and pain
as well so you want the lumbar spine to
be pretty neutral you want to control
too much flexion and too much extension
is a bad thing so let's talk about how
this applies to exercise let's say I'm
going to do a squat or a deadlift all
right I'm in the bottom of a squat here
like this or a deadlift like it's the
bottom of a deadlift okay so this would
be what my my posture would look like
now when you teach proper deadlift
mechanics what you want is you don't
want them just rounding over like this
you know rounding over this is what
they want to do and that's how people
screw up the devil they want to be like
this and just torque at their back like
this and lift all with their back but
you don't let them you teach them how to
hinge at the hips like this but at the
bottom of a deadlift you want to
maintain a slight anterior tilt just
slight not too much because then you get
too much lumbar hyperextension so in a
little bit of anterior tilt you want
lots of hip range of motion and then you
want this spot though the lumbar spine
in neutral so you're going to do a
deadlift little bit of anterior tilt
that helps keep the neutral posture and
then you rise up okay same with a squat
you come down in the bottom of the squat
you know a lot of people have poor
mobility or even problems with their the
hip joint itself and they're pulled into
posterior pelvic tilt which pulls you
into lumbar flexion at the bottom of the
movement but assuming you have good
mobility and good stability you can go
down deep what your spine wants to do
down here is kind of round you don't let
it you keep this into your pelvic tilt
and you come up so the squat the
deadlift if you know the biomechanics
behind the squad the dilip they are
hardest in this hips flexed position
right in here they're hard right here
and as you rise up as you come up they
get easier and easier
you know people can quarter squat a lot
more weight because it just gets easier
and easier on torque loading diminishes
is the squat and the deadlift they have
a an a setting strength curve meaning
you're weaker down here and you're
stronger up here at the lift and that's
because of the loading of the torque
loading of the joints torque loading is
highest here on the hips and also the
lumbar spine and then it reduces as you
rise up okay so the deadlift and a squat
are the best exercises for teaching good
lumbo-pelvic hint mechanics in this low
position if they can do this you know
with heavy loads on their on their back
or in their hands this is a good
indication that they have very good
functioning level pelvic hip complex you
know mechanics well but the top range is
not overloaded you know if you're
standing here in a squat like this with
a bowl on your back you're not really
loaded too much through here the bar is
centered right over the hips and it's
you don't have a lot a large moment here
you don't have a large hip moment or
even that large of a low most fun moment
compared to down here down here you have
up is you know the moment arm is huge
and that is going to create a lot more
muscular contraction in here and you're
going to these muscles are going to
clamp down and create way more
compressive loading and you've got more
shear loading but up top it's a little
bit easier so for the hip joint if you
want strong hip extensors the squad
natella strengthen it from a hips flexed
position but they don't do the job of
straightly in the hips extended position
and the squat dilip do a really good job
of teaching lumbar pelvic stability in a
hips flex position but up top they don't
stress that they don't maximize the
functioning of that okay this is where
other exercise come into play now let's
talk about the hip thrust and the back
extension all right when I do a hip
thrust okay I'm down here like this and
I rise up okay
this is what I hip thrust looks like
okay with the hip thrust
how do people screwed up just like with
the deadlift people screwed up by
flexing their spine you don't let it the
deadlift is a dangerous exercise you
want to go into low more flexion but you
don't let them you don't let your
patients you don't let your clients you
teach them how to control that and keep
a neutral positioning while lifting
heavy loads around the hip joint alright
the opposite can be said for the hip
thrust when you do a hip thrust all
right I'm down here people rise up okay
and then come up and they extend extend
now the sudden they want a hyper extend
here at the spine and they want to go
into aunt your
until here but you don't let them you
are going to make sure that they push
through the glutes they move at the hips
and then keep this in a neutral position
so how do you make sure they keep this
in neutral you want to slight post your
pelvic tilt up top you don't want to be
a hyper-extended like this you want to
post your tilt up top and this helps
hold that neutral position so what
muscles are responsible for the
posterior pelvic tilt the glutes in this
in this situation so strong glutes will
protect the spine so again the hip
thrusts extend extend extend posture
tilt just a little bit to keep this
neutral position so the bottom of a
deadlift you want some slight into your
pelvic tilt just like to keep that
neutral position the top of a hip thrust
you want some slate posture pelvic tilt
to keep this neutral position and that
is optimal lumbar spinal lasari
lumbo-pelvic mechanics but you want the
motion most of the motion occurring at
the hips
alright the hip thrust has way more way
more of hip extension torque loading in
this position right here okay whereas
the squad has the most right here by the
time you get to here in a squat you've
got no torque with the hip thrust you've
got the most torque loading right here
and end range it's the hardest at the
hip joint so if you want to maximize in
range hip strength you need to be doing
hip thrust and also the back extension
which I'll go over in a minute and and
also for teaching proper lumbar pelvic
mechanics you need to be for this range
for this hips extended range you need to
be doing the hip thrust because that's
where this function comes into play all
right now let's go to the back extension
the back extension you're kind of locked
in here and what most people will do
because they hear it called back
extension they want to feel it in the
low back so they will kind of fix their
hips and pelvis and just rotate all in
the spine like this and this is what
their back extension looks like lumbar
flexion lumbar hyperextension while
we've not just Lombardy about the total
spinal flexion spinal hyperextension and
that's not a good that's not good
mechanics what you want to do it's
really hip extension it really should be
called a hip extension and you want to
you want to make sure that the lumbar
spine stays pretty neutral and you're
just moving at the hips let me get the
hip joint just like that now up top in
the back extension you want again you
want to make sure that you're not in
excessive and your pelvic tilt because
that called that angelic tilt and lumbar
hyperextension are associated with each
other just like posterior pelvic tilt
and lumbar flexion are associate with
each other so when you get to the very
top of a back extension you want to make
sure that you're in a little bit of
posterior pelvic tilt right here just to
prevent that hyperextension here so just
make sure that you're again anterior
tilt is this way posterior tilt is this
way you and a lot of people again you'll
test their function you'll tell them I
want you to show pelvic motion like this
and they don't even know how to do it
this is very common with people they
don't know how to move their pelvis they
don't know good motor control at the
pelvis so now let's talk about how this
applies to everyday life and a sports
all right when people pick heavy loads
off the ground they're doing it the best
exercise for teaching that would be like
it
okay but when people are carrying loads
like this
alright farmers walks do the stuff like
that it's important to have you know
strength like that but hip thrust will
make this range strong when you're
sprinting for example all right during
gait and sprinting during gait you know
right up here is thigh reversal this is
not ground contact ground contact
happens right in this range here and you
know probably different angles for
different people but say it's around 30
degrees of hip flexion to around neutral
or hyperextension right there it's all
in here you know this is where you're
producing ground reaction forces
horizontal forces that will pretty push
you forward so if you want to get better
at sprinting get this range really
strong what is the hip what hip exercise
get this range the strongest again it's
hip thrust and then the back extensions
all right
so in sports we're not always in this
flexed position we're up here more more
upright and you know were in this more
hips extended range of motion so whether
you're accelerating or stops top speed
sprinting or even cutting side to side
you're not always bent over so much so
you need to get total hip strength and
total lumbar spinal lumbo-pelvic
stability and so this is why you need a
variety of exercise and I came into the
scene and and kind of strength coaches
put so much of an emphasis on squatting
and dead lifting which is this hips flex
position and this works great for
strengthening here but as you rise up it
leaves the room on the table right in
here
strengthening this to a full degree and
so then you complement those with the
hip thrusts which strengthen this range
of motion the most and the back
extensions which are hardest right here
you know and then you get total hip
strength full-spectrum hip strength and
that's how you you create kind of
optimal lumbo-pelvic hip functioning by
getting the hips that are strong through
a full range of motion but also by using
good form because the good form in the
lumbar spine and pelvic region will
provide that lumbo-pelvic stability
while you move at the hips so I kind of
say still do your squats in Dallas to
get strong in this range adding hip
thrust and back extensions to get strong
in this range and now you've got synergy
there you've got your bases covered so
if you want full range a total
lumbo-pelvic hip complex functioning you
need to do a variety of exercises you
need the Flex position exercise the
squats and Dallas and the extended
position exercise the hip thrusts and
back extensions and then you're going to
produce the best athlete you're going to
have the lower the lowest incidence of
low back pain and you know you're going
to have better posture and you need the
you need a variety of these exercise to
produce the best athlete that's all
there is to it